<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://dric2018.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://dric2018.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2025-08-14T20:14:06+00:00</updated><id>https://dric2018.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Meet Cedric M!
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">L’Intelligence Artificielle à l’Africaine</title><link href="https://dric2018.github.io/blog/2025/une-ia-africaine/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="L’Intelligence Artificielle à l’Africaine" /><published>2025-08-14T19:40:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-08-14T19:40:00+00:00</updated><id>https://dric2018.github.io/blog/2025/une-ia-africaine</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://dric2018.github.io/blog/2025/une-ia-africaine/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="nous-avons-presque-tout-pour-réussir-">Nous avons presque tout pour réussir !</h2>
<p><img src="/assets/img/IC.jpg" alt="Une IA qui nous comprend mieux" /></p>

<p>Dans un monde où les ressources sont limitées et inégalement accessibles, repenser les modèles existants pour des cas d’usage spécifiques est une opportunité stratégique. Cela exige une combinaison d’expertise technique #skills, une compréhension approfondie des problématiques autour de la donnée #data et une infrastructure robuste #compute.</p>

<p>Mais au-delà de ces éléments techniques, une dimension cruciale demeure souvent sous-estimée : la <strong>sensibilité culturelle</strong>. Un modèle d’IA ne peut être véritablement efficace sans tenir compte des contextes sociaux, des valeurs locales et des besoins spécifiques des communautés qu’il vise à servir. En intégrant cette dimension, on réduit les biais, on garantit l’inclusivité et on assure que les solutions répondent à des réalités souvent très complexes.</p>

<p>Et pour aller plus loin, il faut aussi cultiver l’intelligence culturelle. Car la meilleure performance n’est pas seulement une affaire de ressources, mais aussi d’empathie et de respect des différences.</p>

<p><em>L’Afrique, au cœur de l’innovation en IA, incarne l’originalité. Avec nos talents et notre audace, transformons le potentiel en actions palpables. 🌍🚀</em></p>

<p>NB: Post édité avec #Qwen3:8B; Image d’illustration par #GPT5</p>]]></content><author><name>Cédric M.</name></author><category term="opinions" /><category term="policy" /><category term="comments" /><category term="skills" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[L'IA qui correspondra à nos réalité]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ensuring Africa’s Workforce Drives Shared Prosperity</title><link href="https://dric2018.github.io/blog/2025/african-talents/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ensuring Africa’s Workforce Drives Shared Prosperity" /><published>2025-07-16T10:09:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-07-16T10:09:00+00:00</updated><id>https://dric2018.github.io/blog/2025/african-talents</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://dric2018.github.io/blog/2025/african-talents/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="introduction">Introduction</h3>
<p>The assertion that <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">the workforce in the next 30 years will be African</code> reflects compelling demographic projections. According to the UN DESA (2022), Africa will account for over 40% of the world’s working-age population by 2050. Yet demographics alone do not guarantee prosperity. Without the right systems in place, Africa risks becoming a supplier of low-cost labor to global markets—echoing past patterns of extraction and marginalization.</p>

<p>During the transatlantic slave trade and the colonial era, African labor created immense value for European powers, while African societies were left underdeveloped aftrward. As Walter Rodney (1972) wrote in How Europe Underdeveloped Africa, “the greatest contribution Africa made to the world capitalist economy was in the form of labor.” Today, the risk is that without strategic investment and control over value creation, Africa’s youth could again serve global production systems without equitable returns. The danger today is subtler but no less real: unless African economies are empowered to create, retain, and reward value locally, the continent could again become a mere supplier of labor, this time to global markets driven by technology, finance, and innovation elsewhere.</p>

<h3 id="demography-without-agency">Demography Without Agency</h3>
<p>The ILO (2023) notes that <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">85.8% of Sub-Saharan African employment is informal, with limited access to social protections or productive capital</code>. The World Bank’s Human Capital Index (2020) indicates that a child born in Africa today will reach only 40% of their productivity potential due to gaps in health and education. This gap is not inevitable—it reflects policy choices.
<strong>Demographics offer potential</strong>, not inevitability. Without targeted and simultanous investment in education, infrastructure, and digital connectivity, and without structural reforms to unlock entrepreneurship and fair labor practices, African youth will be underutilized or absorbed into <em>precarious</em> global gig economies. The opportunity lies in converting this demographic boom into a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">skills</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">innovation dividend</code>.</p>

<h3 id="policy-imperatives-for-transformative-change">Policy Imperatives for Transformative Change</h3>

<p>To avoid a future of exploitation or marginalization, policymakers must prioritize:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Talent development ecosystems: Invest in technical education, digital skills, and entrepreneurial training from early education through tertiary systems.
Rwanda’s Kigali Innovation City offers a model of integrated investment in STEM education, research, and entrepreneurship, supported by coherent policy and digital infrastructure.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Industrial and digital value chains: Support sectors where Africa can move up the value chain—tech, green energy, agro-processing—not just extractives or assembly.
Ghana’s One District, One Factory initiative attempts to localize production and create jobs through targeted industrialization. For broader replication, this needs to be coupled with access to finance, infrastructure, and skills alignment.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Labor protections and fair trade: Push for global labor standards that protect African workers and advocate for trade deals that include provisions for local value addition.
Policymakers must advocate for fair labor practices in global value chains. The AfCFTA provides an opportunity to strengthen intra-African trade and promote regional value chains that retain more wealth locally.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Diaspora and innovation financing: Create mechanisms to channel diaspora capital and ideas into local enterprises.
Ethiopia’s Homecoming Initiative and Nigeria’s tech startup boom show how diasporic finance and knowledge transfer can catalyze innovation, provided there are transparent governance structures and reliable institutions.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Accelerate Public-Private Partnerships in Education:
India’s IT services boom, built on decades of investment in English-language technical education, offers lessons. African governments can collaborate with industry to develop relevant curricula, vocational training, and certifications aligned with future job markets.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h3 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h3>
<p>Africa’s labor force may become the world’s largest, but whether it becomes a driver of African prosperity depends on choices made today. Demographics alone do not guarantee development. Only through agency, equity, and strategic investment can Africa shape a future where its people are not just the workforce of the world, but also co-authors of global progress.</p>

<p>As the African Development Bank (AfDB, 2022) highlights, critical enablers—electricity access, internet connectivity, credit for SMEs, and gender-inclusive policies—remain uneven. Addressing these bottlenecks is essential to realizing a true demographic dividend.</p>

<h3 id="references">References</h3>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>UN DESA. (2022). World Population Prospects</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>ILO. (2023). World Employment and Social Outlook – Trends</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>World Bank. (2020). The Human Capital Index</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Rodney, W. (1972). How Europe Underdeveloped Africa</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>AfDB. (2022). African Economic Outlook</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Kigali Innovation City – <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=DAQgz1DIgIs">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=DAQgz1DIgIs</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>AfCFTA – <a href="https://au-afcfta.org">https://au-afcfta.org</a></p>
  </li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Cédric M.</name></author><category term="opinions" /><category term="policy" /><category term="comments" /><category term="skills" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A commentary about Africa's potential for tech talents]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Digital Umuganda 2025 Kinyarwanda ASR Hack</title><link href="https://dric2018.github.io/blog/2025/jupyter-notebook/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Digital Umuganda 2025 Kinyarwanda ASR Hack" /><published>2025-06-11T03:57:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-06-11T03:57:00+00:00</updated><id>https://dric2018.github.io/blog/2025/jupyter-notebook</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://dric2018.github.io/blog/2025/jupyter-notebook/"><![CDATA[<p>After spending some time going through the competitions, I realized the entry barrier may be a bit high and prepared a short tutorial to help folks get started.
The Kaggle notebook can be found at <a href="https://www.kaggle.com/code/cedricmanouan11/kinasr2025-data-modules-eda/noteboo">https://www.kaggle.com/code/cedricmanouan11/kinasr2025-data-modules-eda/notebook</a>.</p>




<div
  class="jupyter-notebook"
  style="position: relative; width: 100%; margin: 0 auto;">
  <div class="jupyter-notebook-iframe-container">
    <iframe
      src="/assets/jupyter/kinasr2025-data-modules-eda.ipynb.html"
      style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; border-style: none;"
      width="100%"
      height="100%"
      onload="this.parentElement.style.paddingBottom = (this.contentWindow.document.documentElement.scrollHeight + 10) + 'px'"></iframe>
  </div>
</div>]]></content><author><name>Cédric M.</name></author><category term="educational" /><category term="code" /><category term="tech" /><category term="engineering" /><category term="jupyter" /><category term="competition" /><category term="speech" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[An example EDA and implementation of data modules to facilitate participation in ASR hackathon.]]></summary></entry></feed>